record
hello sir hello yeah we I met you you
contacted me after I did an interview
with David and we had a we just don't
right into it
and you're you're just so people who are
watching know who you are
if they don't know already you started
how I met you through rubble wisdom
which is the channel that you started
correct yeah started with David yeah and
then you also are doing um something
something around psychedelics and
therapy or something like that right
yeah yeah I that's a world I'm really
involved in I'm one of the organizers of
a big conference here in London that
happens every two years for a convention
which is about 1,500 people this last
summer and it's kind of grown and my
wife works in psychedelic research as
well and a lot of my friends do and when
I was younger when I was sort of early
20s I wrote a novel which was set around
that whole area so it's been nice to do
a podcast as well about visionary art
which is sort of the art from that world
so it's been really yeah it's been a big
part of my life for quite a long time
well kind of you kind of trippy aren't
you yeah my first conversation I really
appreciated her first conversation we
just don't write into it started talking
about Gnosticism and temporal temporal
time temporality and had goosebumps and
sparks it was like as like oh yeah
there's something familiar about you
know it's there's a familiarity I have
with you that I that isn't justified
right by any rational or reasonable
standards
but there's a there's something I sense
in what you're up to and who you are and
I think just the way that you
respond to me so this word but also
respond in an interesting response that
you have to life to like one of them
which is starting a whole channel which
I'm sure has been a whole ride that I
want to talk with you about and also I'm
starting starting psychedelic
organizations write writing novels is
that it's an interesting response to to
existence
hmm really interesting that that phrase
responds to life or responds to
existence really stuck at me as soon as
you said it I'm kind of wondering like
huh
I don't think I've ever well I don't
know how often I conceptualize the
things that I'm doing or thinking or
whatever it might be as a response to
life although I think that rings true
there's a sort of I just I don't know
I'm kind of thinking out loud this is
really interesting because I suppose it
is a response to life it's a response to
I guess everything what we're all doing
is somehow responding to our environment
and it's weird for me because it doesn't
it's weird for me that that is weird
like it doesn't necessarily feel like a
response it just feels like um stuff
that feels like the natural thing to do
that makes sense it's like yeah you know
for example with the psychedelics it was
having an experience and I was like 18
and I remember really vividly that being
an experience of homecoming and a sense
of oh of course
yeah of course this is like my first
mushroom experience it was just that
sense of naturalness of yeah this yes
reality this is this is the this is more
of reality and of course I had a feeling
that it had always been there and was
ever-present and I was remembering a
lovely word there kind of remembering
putting a piece of yourself back and I
guess a lot of this stuff has been since
then has also been in a sense feeling
like no like it just all comes like so
easily and it's just like in some kind
of total flow that's not the case at all
but at least some sense of
things just seeming obviously like the
thing to do in that moment mmm much pain
it's alright welcome but eventually
coming to the point of oh yeah okay this
feels like the thing to do
yeah well I just looked at you just I
just looked at your response to my
saying TT you noticing that I used the
word response anyone huh I've never
thought about it like that basically
that's kind of strange that I wouldn't
but I guess it is and then you went he
said he also said it was weird that
don't think about it like that and then
you just move towards it so just I
that's what I mean well it's fun I
father really fun I find that like you
know as David and I are trained in our
counseling training was very much based
around this mythical inquiry which is
from the Diamond essence age almost a
tradition and I remembered like doing a
lot of that finding it just really fun
like just just kind of following the
threads you know whether there's like a
somatic thread or bits like a cognitive
thread and I never thought like that or
whatever it might be my father
really enjoyable like this I just find
enjoyable as a way to approach things if
I'm in the right space and I'm not
always in the right space for that which
i think is probably true of most of us
but I know and that's that in itself as
a thing of noticing when I'm not in a
space of inquiry when I'm shut down and
I'm feeling defensive or not open or
whatever it is but right now I feel like
in that space which is good yeah that's
impressive especially considering that
you're moving yeah into a boat into a
boat you have to downsize in order to do
it yeah today I'm our version of
Craigslist which is called Gumtree which
is uh yeah yeah just a whole process of
stripping away stuff when it feels for
me really good like really liberating
maybe too strong word for it but like
yeah it's somewhat liberating you know
just this kind of getting more nimble
and the book or it's like in a boat by
technically we can move the boat it's a
fixed position but even just knowing
that is possible to go you know and go
down the canal is that is that's that's
interesting well you know I I was
wondering about you know when you talked
about your
[Music]
what you and David did with like a
diamond heart work and the the thing
about inquiry and funk just following a
thread and following your interest and
that your responsiveness to that right
like it seems it seems to me that it
seems to me that if I just looking from
the outside and I look like the way that
rebel wisdom unfolds it is that it looks
like a fractal to me that in a certain
sense that what you guys seem to be
doing is basically following a thread
and you are you are um I think
increasingly in my experience us more
and more self-aware and inclusive of
yourself in your own interest in the
process as it seems like that the
channel you're both creating a channel
but you're also listening for what the
channel is as you're as you're creating
it so it has this kind of self-awareness
so it's been really interesting to watch
but I it sounds I'm imagining that
that's very reflective of you isn't it
yeah I think it's reflective of both me
and David in our attitudes and something
that has brought us together as well and
you're right there there is definitely
the experience and following a thread
from the entire the entire Genesis
channel I mean it's interesting because
before the media channel rebel wisdom
that Bryan existed for a few months
before that because we came up with it
for our men's work we did have a David
had some one thing when we were out at
this kind of Nordic men's gathering
which had been sort of viral on Facebook
it was a cop that's cool but then there
was a thread of you know he went to go
see a Jordan Peterson talk and that was
a that almost didn't happen as well
because he had some visa problem at the
airport I wasn't working and George
Buddhism wasn't hadn't exploded yet you
know it was sort of following that Fred
and then you know the beginning of the
channel there was a lot of like
exploring that phenomena and then there
was following the threat of the IDW the
intellectual dark web and then following
the threat of the I guess what we're
looking at now the kind of emerge and
sense making space that you're in as
well you know there's a new group of
people and then it always feels like
what is yeah it's following what's
emerging and then one of the things we
often say is like we're like we've just
got to ride the wave like weird like no
one is the wave but the wave is there
and so that the skill is to be able to
feel into like feel it as I guys feeling
- what's moving way
and for me personally that's like that's
kind of an entirely intuitive process
and there's a there's a sort of
intuitive trust and literally just
following my feeling of not really
feeling that conversation not really
feeling but that's a complete picture of
this or that and I'm doing it obviously
like the mind comes into it very much as
well but the very first impulse is does
it feel right yeah which is often
negated in a lot of well businesses and
I don't know cultural institutions but
for me is crucial crucial yeah see that
that that initial felt sense or like how
does it feel right or not that initial
kind of meeting seems seems to me like
one of the things that is it's it's
interesting to watch you guys right and
to be a part of it as well but this
quality of what what is it that you're
feeling into right and and this kind of
coordinated coupled miss with the world
and I would imagine there's a quality of
you know I wanted to ask you about this
to adjust your your personal experience
of doing the channel like that felt
sense which you can do that internally
which you've been you've been doing but
there's there's also this way in which
you're doing it in relationship to what
you're showing you know a hundred
thousand people on your channel or
something like that there's a the deepen
tuition or the deepening of that felt
sense right in that coordinated
activities a real mysterious thing when
you look at well what is it how do you
know to move this way versus that way
and like and as you go through time you
can become more and more attune to that
right but there's never ever you never
reach the end of of it but I'm wondering
about like what's the ride been like for
you personally in the development of
that like when you interview or when you
set up interviews or the conflicts that
come up in in making the channel and
your relationship with David like I get
the sense that you are that what's
unfolding on the channel is is very
attuned to the work that you guys are
doing on yourselves yeah yes it has to
be that's a really interesting question
and it is like there's a Pandora's box
in my chest feeling into it just like a
lot of stuff a lot of experience over
the last I spent about two years I guess
yeah it's been it has been like in
itself a process of inquiry and personal
growth you know and like David and I
have gone through big inquiries together
and big like all the ups and downs of
being close friends and kind of being
running a project and and and also being
involved in what is effectively a very
fast-paced emergent cultural phenomena
you know so all of that happening at the
same time for me it's been like a mix of
exciting and like activating in the
sense of like activating parts
unresolved aspects of myself it has a
way of bringing that out mmm coming up
whatever
[Music]
aspects of my ego structure um you know
like exploring things like I need to be
seen that's part of my personality and
like going to shine and be seen
exploring letting go and surrendering
I'm feeling and that whole pro
as a feeling into stuff like that's not
necessarily my natural way of being
although with with meditation X type of
meditating for like my whole adult life
so in that sense I know how to do it I
don't know if it's my default place you
know
like issues of what's it what's the
default hmm you seem you see it see I
felt into a dispute it feels like you're
kind of a grappler like you don't you
definitely seem to be less agreeable
your temperamentally like it's already
like you ready that to go at it or
something like a wrestle with it or
something like that that's yeah that
feels very true for me and that's
interesting you you pick up on that
there's some kind of internal um
frustration or energy with just wanting
to get grapple is a good good word
I've grappling test you know I'd rather
shake something to see if it breaks and
then if it does okay that doesn't work
and do something else that's kind of a
default so being patient slowing down
feeling into surrendering all of those
require paradoxically quite a lot of
effort there's actually a line I think
is from the daodejing or is it from one
of one Taoist possible just says when
effort has been used to achieve
effortlessness then you've grasped it
let me get a bit you know and that stays
with me oh I thought a bit I think this
morning or maybe the day before I came
to me and I was like yeah that's that's
a real yeah I mean I really sticks with
me yeah something about I really felt
kind of young you know where he talks
about that sense of where you know the
second half of life for your psyche does
a flip-flop right where um what ends up
enlightening you is not what you're good
at
but your inferior functions is you would
say you know I'm sensing I can hear that
in the backdrop right of my awareness as
you're talking about like yeah I
normally want to like like fighting
punch it and wrestle with it and right
but there's I'm learning patience
laughter and in fact I'd say koenz to
myself to remember and I I think where
my attention goes and listening to you
is I'm
there must be something that makes that
struggle that it is to be patient and to
be more listening or or or what you're
talking about that would that would call
that call that struggle out in you like
what's the what's the sense what's the
thing on the horizon that
that has you um not punch things and
instead allow things and be interested
is very interesting I get this emailing
well yeah like it was image though I get
this image when you say what's that
thing on the horizon of this kind of
like mmm I was in Estonia at one time at
midsummer and it was about probably the
furthest north I've ever been and even
though they don't have full light all
night long like you would further up and
say like northern Sweden they have this
little strip of light over the horizon
and that image just came to me as here
saying that it said what is that thing I
don't know that's such a mystery right
like that's the kind of that's that's
the kind of into eternal mystery because
there there does seem to be this kind of
sense of some Co Heat coherence or
cohesion pulling from the future I was
like Big Idea Terence Mckenna had you
know this attractor at the end of time
the set of things moving forward things
are being drawn in and that's always
been yeah an interesting idea for me I
know I kind of drift in and out of
connecting with it but as you're talking
about it I'm thinking like what I linked
it to myself personally like where does
it like to me personally like my future
self in a way or a potential future self
calling that feels more real to me even
though it's kind of hazy still and
mysterious
it's like there's some potentiality yes
you know drawing meat towards some
version of myself
and that seems like really trippy and
mysterious as I talk about it like it's
just so yeah very mysterious so as you
as you talk about it it it
is kind of a mystery to you huh there's
a that I think I guess this kind of
circles back to the beginning of the
conversation where I think what I mean
by response right is as you could say my
understanding is is like every single
movement that we do is a response that
to the finding ourselves existing it's
like in this weird couple this with your
environment in the world and with each
other and all the different real like
network of relations that go all the way
down so what I think when I'm he like
that's I think where my question was
coming from was that kind of
understanding of like oh yeah like I
think one on one level I'm hearing it's
been a personal ride up to this point
and it's it's been it's taken something
to develop on one level there's
something innate there right that draws
you to it in the first place but I would
imagine that Co fashioning and Co
shaping of you know in this case like
the channel like rebel wisdom right if
we take that example it's it's it's
called it's like it's called forth
patience and things that are not
necessarily naturally temperamental for
you to cultivate great and I think in
just the responsiveness right seems to
announce and some kind of understanding
that makes the response makes you
respond that way so like when you talk
about like the mystery well that's
missed its mysterious right however your
responsiveness knows to respond to it
like that sense of it right
what is that sense that is super
interesting what is that sense yeah it's
like
kind of feeling of okay I'm trying to
knock this out feels like to me there's
some kind of feeling of knowing knowing
that the thing happening is a thing
being called for that's needed because
there's some sense of like underlying
rightness to it for exactly even even if
it's actually really stressful and
unpleasant like for example I like
personality was so before rebel wisdom I
was writing novels or trying to write
novels much a little bit about mini
burger like many writers burnout and was
also working 9 to 5 like pretty high
intensity was a Sales Director training
agencies I was doing before that I was
doing that part-time and running a
meditation school with my wife so always
doing lots of these things were quite
individualist I was very individual and
it was I'm gonna do it myself and if I
don't do it by myself
then I didn't really do it you know this
is a kind of a psychological constructor
Mike doesn't really count unless you
manage to do it yourself
yeah just like a self belief yeah the
process of rebel wisdom in part has been
one of being like its co-creative in so
many ways it's co-creative because it's
me and David it's also co-created
because we are co-creating with the
world around us to make the channel and
to cover stuff the kind of direction
we're moving in is much more around
encouraging co-creation in our community
and accept all together working with
people all of those things are growth
areas for me personally so you know
there's times where I just want to go oh
my god I just want to do everything
myself I just wanted I just don't want
to have to just like you know check in
with other people in anyway I just want
to go lone-wolf just do all of that so
even though that feeling can be really
strong sometimes there's just to circle
back there's this feeling of but this is
exactly what I need this is the
rightness on it like this situation I am
in
yeah right now is exactly where I want
to be and it's also where part of my ego
doesn't want to be but within all that
kind of mishmash there's some underlying
sense of like yeah this is right this is
good for me
this is where I need to be going and
this is what needs to be happening right
now
so that is the feeling that like that's
partly what the thing is I think yes so
this is it like this is struck by the
thing that you said like the high pupil
is that there's an underlying feeling of
rightness something's gotta be right
right that then allows you to it sounds
like it allows you to tune into or
grapple with yourself and doing things
that don't aren't necessarily what you
want to do in that moment it sounds like
it sounds like
so it sounds like something about you
mentioned the struck the ego structure
of being the end of it just an
interesting way of putting it of like if
I didn't do it I didn't do it myself
right so there's a kind of a set I what
I'm hearing is that there's a you found
in some ways I would imagine that has
occurred that do it myself has occurred
to be the thing to sacrifice yeah right
where it used to be the thing to make
sure of and now it's the thing because
that's the big question I'll often
dislike if you can do anything well
what's the right sacrifice that's not
necessarily that obvious but it seems
like you're finding some there's some
kind of sense of sacrificing what used
to be the goal is now that's really
hearing stood that takes me aback a
little bit because there's something
about sacrifice as a concept and as a
practice that I value very highly hmm
way you've just framed that feels very
it a feels true and almost like a new
way of seeing it where I'm like it's
something relaxes in me a little bit I
notice like my shoulders relaxed a bit
I'm like well yeah cool ok yeah so there
is a yeah yeah that's cool yeah and
that's there's that feels quite a live
framed like that for me because there's
something implicit in the idea of
sacrifice is that is for something too
but for me at least and so it's like ok
yes that does feel like that is the
sacrifice that's the kind of growth but
what's the sacrifice for and that's
where we're getting this event horizon
where I'm like I don't know but that's
really interesting you know that's the
kind of our process of becoming I guess
I would want to know was that you bore
oh yes yes and where
I'm as curious about for you like which
part of what you're doing right now like
with the channel or the other things
that you're doing you know what like
what is the experience that you have of
doing interviews of just like the
structure of doing interviews what
that's like for you what's been
challenging for you around that like if
it's been challenging like the process
of just going and interviewing people
right and fall all of it like being
aware of like there's you know I'm sure
there's monetary stuff in there there's
like you know like there's knowing that
there's like it a listening that you're
speaking into there so I've noticed for
me just doing having just started doing
these things and and and putting them
out online there's like it's opened up
worlds like that I'm still finding out
about and it's I can tell I can tell for
myself that it's been a very self
revealing process in a lot of ways like
it's helped me see a lot of myself but
also kind of see more of what I'm up to
in a very magnified way just just in the
process of interviewing people right if
you want to call that to call this
interviewing like I'm just curious for
you what is that that part of it been
like for you that's been an interesting
journey because like there's I'm more by
background a writer and there's other
things but David has you know David has
that kind of bust in his whole career
writers is thank you yeah in part
interviewing people there's been a
learning process for me which has been
quite cool of learning some basics as
well
when I did my podcast visionary artist
podcast it was it was interviews but
it's also kind of like conversations you
know and they were Arden everyone was an
artist so it was kind of different
sitting down with a different kind of
thinker and I'm developing that skill of
figuring out
where's the gold in this you know
where's the gold in this conversation
and then also I noticed that from like
between now and maybe like this time
last year I can notice this development
in my own style on my own comfort level
with it where I remember kind of before
a kind of rigidly feeling like okay I've
got these 10 questions I gotta hit these
questions you know I've got to kind of
move it along and yeah I'll be receptive
to what's happening but I gotta come
back to these questions I don't know
it's very much more a process of just
loosening with it and coming into more
of that kind of inquiring space know um
you know this for me is very enjoy this
this for me feels like the level of flow
that I've really enjoy and that kind of
pulls things out and apart some people
are more that's not so much their
comfort zone you know some people if
they're know a scientist of some kind or
whatever it might be roar have made
their career quad cognitively they might
not be as comfortable with getting into
that kind of more flowing space but I
always have this urge to to have a kind
of conversation with someone that looks
a bit like a little bit like this or a
little bit like the kind of
conversations that happened in our men's
weekends but there's just a real
openness curiosity so that's like an
ongoing like process for me of how do
you how do you drop into that with
anyone can you I don't know but like
it's it's definitely been so there's
that side of it there's that kind of
practical and stylistic side and then
there's also yeah there's also I mean
just as a as a process it's really
interesting to observe how they move and
how predictable they are how critical
they are which ones people end up really
liking which can sometimes we arrest
prized like our one with doe Xin Zen
master that was that was like a
breakaway hit you know that we just did
not expect has like 350,000 views now
maybe 5,000 and who knows just kind of
yeah so there's this kind of still this
kind of total feeling of mystery to all
of it
oh you know what's gonna line of what is
yeah oh and I bet it's uh has it been a
process of listening to what lands but
also following like is it I could
imagine that there's maybe been some
dissonance sometimes we're following
that felt sense of what wants to unfold
and then looking at what landed his most
popular is there if you guys confronted
any sense like oh yeah I feel like I
want to go over here but like this is
getting the most views I could imagine
that being attention yeah it is it is
not like a major ongoing tension but
it's certainly a bear it's certainly
present because there's always there's
always the worry of like getting kind of
captured by your audience and doing
things that you think they're gonna like
and then you start drifting away from
your integrity and also you start losing
kind of creativity about happens and
I've seen like decent amount of YouTube
channels where that has happened and you
know I yeah I mean it's something that
we want to do stuff that's relevant to
people and that lots of people watch but
also I think what comes up for me as I
talk about that a little bit is that you
can all you can have both that doesn't
have to be the limitation and that's
something we talk about because you turn
on the TV channel there's like ten
different shows and they're all
different that one's a drama one's a
comedy so that's something we've talked
about a lot recently is how do we make
space for everything you know maybe
there's a film that three thousand
people want to watch because I just are
deeply into the history of Christianity
or something like that or met if it also
fee then we want to watch something more
around what's going on with culture
right now and on current events yeah
it's a when I think I heard and tell me
if I heard this or tell me
if you said this I definitely heard this
this is when you're talking about like
the becoming the process of becoming an
interviewer right and then how like on
one hand I'm from with David in his
background you've learned a lot you've
appreciated learning a lot of having the
sense he said finding the gold in this
in this thinker or this person or this
conversation and then and then he talked
about at first there was a process of
being a bit rigid right because it was
new to like have ten questions or
ordered to be oriented that way and that
sounds like you've started to like he
started to learn how to work the clutch
you know without having to think about
it like they're syncing up so there's
like unconscious competence that's
starting to write or conscious
competence or it's becoming you know
more embodied and they need to eat I saw
you have this little smirk right you're
like but really like I like I think you
said something I like tapping into that
space of discovery and then you
mentioned kind of the flow that we're in
right now and
and then you then you went yeah I'm
trying to find I heard you say I'm
trying to find you didn't say this but I
heard a sweet spot mm-hmm ray of
where there's this kind of awareness of
a structure right of some kind but also
like oh I want to be surprised or I want
to hit that hit that thing I'm most
interested in what what is that thing
that you're most interested in that
you're almost like a like a mischievious
like grin on your face I almost stopped
you said what is that good it's it's
something like a moment of like a moment
where if it were a movie or a play you
go did not see that coming
you know that's what I'm that's what I
was looking for when I was writing
stories it's it's kind of what I'm
always looking for is some element of
being blown away a little bit surprise
is like wow like kind of hit hit by a
ton of bricks the kind of thing in a in
a conversation or a moment where you
would like if you saw it you turn to
your friend and at the same time you
both look at each other no it's like
it's that kind of yeah magic that I
think I'm always keen to see or keen to
experience not just in like interviewing
someone or or whatever it might be but
like in life as well you know it's it's
something around novelty and something
around surprise delight you know it's I
love a twist
at the end of the book or Ruby you know
like that's my one of my favorite things
are very well done twist yeah not that
but that surprised that the light
doesn't have to be like a single moment
you know like I read a book last year
called the 7 deaths of Evelyn Hardcastle
and very briefly it's sort of like
Agatha Christie meets inception so this
guy's trying to solve a murder but he
keeps jumping into the bodies of other
people at this mansion and he so he's
like meeting himself and then has to
give herself a clue and like later at
the book so as I was reading that book I
was in a permanent state of delight
because it was like what
someone juggle I was like oh my god I
can't believe this guy's pulling off
this book this is insane um and it was
great because I read an article about it
a few maybe like six months later and
the guy said like the book almost broken
like he had a wall full of post-it notes
and like stream is going because the
complexity of it is incredible and he
never at his flawless it never breaks
and it's also a really good book so not
for me like you could take that and put
it into an interview you could take that
put it somewhere else but like that's
that's a real sweet spot right that's a
real sweet spot of of complete control
but also freedom in that yeah and that I
think it is something like sweets porn
I've asked the word you started with and
that's what it feels like it's like it's
just like a trapeze artist just on the
line between order and chaos yeah in
right like right now where are we at
with the sweet spot what do you say I
don't know I feel pretty good yeah
I had this I was noticing when you were
talking about
oh that like oh I didn't see that coming
like that thing that goes that that like
it's it's it's an interesting thing that
you talked about because on some level I
didn't it what I what I where the gold
is right good this that's worth doing it
it's worthless having you even calibrate
between structure and formlessness and
all the different things that you're
talking about
is this sense of awareness for what you
can't be aware of but you know to orient
around and it's it's interesting because
I'm I'm I'm kind of harkening back to
this notion of the my question before
which is like what is the thing that's
just beyond the horizon that seems to be
calling out sacrificing what your
strength sacrificing like for the sake
of and I am wondering that's like I had
a very similar feeling
presencing that horizon and this almost
a bodily sense I get this embodied sense
of like okay that's a little bit to the
left or the right like this this
orientation for something that you by
definition you can't know about ahead of
time but you know enough to be oriented
around it and calibrate around it yeah
that's a mystery - it's like a dance
it feels like like I'm you're saying
that I think about the process of a
dance you know yeah steps but also
there's flow yeah yeah thanks talking
with you my friend very nice talking
with you as well I enjoyed this
congratulations on on moving and moving
to a place that moves yeah thank you I'm
looking forward to it yes and yet you
have to go now right I do I have to go
and predictably do moving related stuff
so okay
may this be the beginning of much yes
I'd love to do it again for sure
absolutely my friend here